Performing Database Backups

Multiplexing Control Files Using an Spfile

1. Alter the spfile while the database is still open:
SQL> ALTER SYSTEM SET CONTROL_FILES =
‘/ora01/oradata/MYDB/ctrlMYDB01.ctl‘,
‘/ora02/oradata/MYDB/ctrlMYDB02.ctl‘,
‘/ora03/oradata/MYDB/ctrlMYDB03.ctl‘,
‘/ora04/oradata/MYDB/ctrlMYDB04.ctl‘ SCOPE=SPFILE;
This parameter change takes effect only after the next instance restart by using the SCOPE=SPFILE qualifier. The contents of the binary spfile are changed immediately, but the old specification of CONTROL_FILES is used until the instance is restarted.
2. Shut down the database:
SQL> SHUTDOWN NORMAL
3. Copy an existing control file to the new location:
$ cp /ora01/oradata/MYDB/ctrlMYDB01.ctl /ora04/oradata/MYDB/ctrlMYDB04.ctl
4. Start the instance:
SQL> STARTUP

If your database is in noarchivelog mode, you cannot do open backups. Backups may only be made with operating system commands when the database is shut down, or with RMAN when it is mounted.

User-Managed Consistent Backups (Also known as: closed/cold/consistent/offline) 
■ Copy the controlfile(s).
■ Copy the datafiles.
■ Copy the online redo log files.

Optionally, copy the online redo log files as well and the tempfiles. And don’t  forget the parameter file, though strictly speaking that is not part of the database.

This SQL*Plus script (run while the database is open) will generate a Windows shell script that will perform the backup using operating system commands:

spool cold_backup.bat
select 'copy '||name||' d:\backup' from v$datafile
union all
select 'copy '||name||' d:\backup' from v$controlfile
union all
select 'copy '||member||' d:\backup' v$logfile;
create pfile='d:\backup\spfile_backup.ora' from spfile;
spool off


****** You also need to back up the parameter file (init file or spfile) and password file. -- biju thomas book
Including the online redo log file members in the backup is, strictly speaking, optional. This is because they will never be needed if the database is shut down cleanly.

Most DBAs will always include the online redo log file members in the backup, because it makes restore simpler and also means that if something goes wrong with the shutdown script such that it is not in fact a clean shutdown, then they will be available for recovery.

There is no necessity ever to back up the tempfiles because they contain no data that has any persistence beyond the lifetime of the session that created them. If a tempfile gets damaged, the quickest recovery method is to drop it and recreate it; the recreation will be much quicker than a restore, and so there is no point in backing them up.

An example of an operating system script that could be launched by the operating

system job scheduler to automate the backup is
sqlplus <<!
connect / as sysdba
@generate_cold_backup_bat.sql
shutdown immediate
!
cold_backup.bat
sqlplus <<!
connect / as sysdba
startup
!

Server-Managed Consistent Backups

An RMAN offline consistent backup has one crucial difference from an operating system offline consistent backup: it can be accomplished only when the database is in mount mode. This is because RMAN needs to read the controlfile in order to find the datafiles. If an operating system backup were attempted in mount mode, it would be invalid (though the DBA wouldn’t realize this until he/she tried to restore) because even in mount node the controlfile might be written to while being copied. The copy would then be inconsistent, and therefore useless. RMAN avoids the problem by taking a read-consistent snapshot of the controlfile and backing that up.

An RMAN backup is launched from the RMAN executable. The RMAN executable is a tool supplied by Oracle and installed into the Oracle Home. RMAN logs on to the database (like any other user process) and then launches additional server processes to copy files.

This is an RMAN script for performing an offline whole full backup:

run {
shutdown immediate;
startup mount;
allocate channel d1 type disk;
backup as backupset database
format 'd:\backup\offline_full_whole.bus';
alter database open;
}

allocate channel d1 type disk; -- Here the script launches a server process to perform the backup. This is known as a channel. In this case, the channel is a disk channel because the backup is being directed to disk; the alternative channel type is SBT_TAPE, which is used for backups directed to a tape device.

backup as backupset database -- This command launches a backup operation. This will be of type BACKUPSET. Backup sets are an RMAN-proprietary structure that can combine many input files into one output file. Backup sets have other advantages, such as compression (not enabled in this example) and the  ability to reduce the size of the backup by ignoring blocks in the input datafiles that have never been used. The keyword DATABASE instructs RMAN to back up the entire set of datafiles and the controlfile. RMAN will never back up online redo log file members or tempfiles.

format 'd:\backup\offline_full_whole.bus'; -- FORMAT keyword names the file that will contain the backup set.

An operating system command that could be scheduled to run this script is
rman target sys/oracle@orcl11g @offline_full_whole.rman
This command launches the RMAN executable, with the SYS login (necessary because of the SHUTDOWN and STARTUP commands)

RMAN can generate three types of backup:
■ A backup set is a proprietary format that can contain several files and will not include never-used blocks.
■ A compressed backup set has the same content as a backup set, but RMAN will apply a compression algorithm as it writes out the backup set.
■ An image copy is a backup file that is identical to the input file. An image copy is immediately interchangeable with its source, whereas to extract a file from a backup set requires an RMAN restore operation.

From an operating system prompt, launch the RMAN executable (it is called rman on Unix and Linux, rman.exe on Windows) and connect using operating system authentication. The command is

rman target /
Perform a full backup. The command is
backup database;
This will, by default, back up the entire database to the flash recovery area.

Back Up Your Database Without Shutting It Down (open/hot/inconsistent/online)

User-Managed Open Backups
An open backup with operating system commands is three steps:
■ Back up the controlfile with ALTER DATABASE BACKUP CONTROLFILE.
■ Copy the datafiles, while they are in backup mode.
■ Archive the online redo log files.

To back up the controlfile while it is open, use an ALTER DATABASE command. There are two versions:

alter database backup controlfile to 'file_name' ;
alter database backup controlfile to trace as 'file_name' ;

The first of these command will take a read-consistent snapshot of the controlfile and back that up to the file_name specified. This is often referred to as a binary copy. It will be byte-for-byte the same as the live controlfile, and the snapshot mechanism ensures that it is consistent.

The second command constructs a CREATE CONTROLFILE command and saves it in a script called file_name. This script can be executed while the instance is in NOMOUNT mode to create a new controlfile, with the same contents as the original controlfile from which it was generated. This script is an ASCII file that can be viewed (and edited) with any test editor.

The datafiles can be copied with any operating system utility, but before making the copy they must be put into backup mode with an ALTER TABLESPACE command:
alter tablespace tablespace_name begin backup;

This command has two effects. First, it forces a partial checkpoint: all the dirty buffers in the database buffer cache that contain blocks from the tablespace’s datafiles are written to disk.

Second, it adjusts the redo generation mechanism for changes made to blocks from those datafiles. This is necessary to manage the situation where a block is updated while it is being copied, and it requires some explanation.

Consider what actually happens if you copy a file with an operating system utility while the file is in use. Take an example where the operating system block size is 512 bytes (the default on many Unix and Windows systems) but the Oracle block size, as determined by the DB_BLOCK_SIZE parameter, is 8 KB. Each Oracle block will be sixteen operating system blocks.

If the file is many megabytes big, this copy will take several seconds or minutes to complete, and during that time it is more than likely that DBWn will flush some changed blocks from the database buffer cache to the datafile; the file will be changed while it is being copied. The granularity of the operating system copy is the operating system block, but the granularity of the DBWn write is the Oracle block. It is thus possible that the copy command will take the first part of an Oracle block, then DBWn will overwrite the whole Oracle block, and the copy command will then take the remaining part of the Oracle block. You have no control over this;

So in the output file produced by the copy, there will be what is called a fractured block: parts of it will be as of different versions. Such a block is completely useless; you have a data corruption in your backup.

If you are using operating system utilities to perform online backups, you avoid the fractured block problem by putting the tablespace containing the datafile into backup mode, with an ALTER TABLESPACE...BEGIN BACKUP command, for the duration of the copy. From that point on, whenever a server process updates a block in the database buffer cache, rather than writing out the minimal change vector to the log buffer it will write out the complete block image to the log buffer. This block image will be read-consistent. 

Thus you accept that an online backup will have fractured blocks, but Oracle can repair them if necessary. The downside of this is that the rate of redo generation may accelerate astronomically while the tablespace is in backup mode: 8KB for each change, instead of just a few bytes. You may find that you are log-switching thirty times an hour rather than thirty times a day when you put tablespaces into backup mode, with a consequent drop in performance.

This SQL*Plus script will generate a script that will perform full online backup of the database:

set serveroutput on
declare
	cursor ts_cursor is
		select * from dba_tablespaces where contents <> 'TEMPORARY';
	cursor df_cursor (ts_name varchar2) is
		select * from dba_data_files where tablespace_name = ts_name;
begin
	for t in ts_cursor loop
	dbms_output.put_line('alter tablespace '||t.tablespace_name||' begin backup;');
	for f in df_cursor(t.tablespace_name) loop
	dbms_output.put_line('host cp -p ''' || f.file_name || ''' C:\oracle\BackUp\SET1');
	end loop;
	dbms_output.put_line(
	'alter tablespace '||t.tablespace_name||' end backup;');
	end loop;
	dbms_output.put_line('alter database backup controlfile to trace as
	''/backup/controlfile.trace'';');
	dbms_output.put_line(
	'alter database backup controlfile to ''C:\oracle\BackUp\SET1\controlfile.binary'';');
	dbms_output.put_line('create pfile=''C:\oracle\BackUp\SET1\spfile_backup.ora''
	from spfile;');
end;
/

Server-Managed Open Backups
An absolutely reliable open backup can be made with RMAN with a two-word command: BACKUP DATABASE.

This RMAN script performs a full whole online backup of the database and the archive log files:

run {
allocate channel t1 type sbt_tape;
allocate channel t2 type sbt_tape;
backup as compressed backupset filesperset 4 database;
backup as compressed backupset archivelog all delete all input;
}

The use of multiple channels (possible related to the number of tape drives in the library) will parallelize the backup operation, which should make it run faster. The first backup command backs up the complete database, but rather than putting every file into one huge (even though compressed) backup set, it instructs RMAN to divide the database into multiple backup sets of four files each; this can make restore operations faster than if all the files are in one backup set. 
The second backup command will back up all the archive log files, removing them from disk as it does so.

When using RMAN for open backups, there is no requirement to put the tablespaces into backup mode. This is because RMAN, being an Oracle-aware tool, will detect fractured blocks if they occur, and will retry the block copy until it gets a consistent version.

Create Incremental Backups
Incremental backups can be made with server-managed backups, but not with usermanaged backups.

Incremental backups must always be as backup sets or compressed backup sets. It is logically impossible to make an image copy incremental backup, because an incremental backup can never be identical to the source file. If it were, it wouldn’t be incremental.

An incremental backup relies on a starting point that contains all blocks: this is known as the incremental level 0 backup. Then an incremental level 1 backup will extract all blocks that have changed since the last level 1 backup, or the last level 0 backup if there have been no intervening level 1 backups. A cumulative backup will extract all blocks that have changed since the last level 0 backup, irrespective of whether there have been any level 1 backups in the meantime.

An RMAN command to make a level 0 backup is
backup as backupset incremental level 0 database;
This command relies on configured defaults for launching channels, for the number of files to place in each backup set, and to where the backup set will be written. The backup set will contain all blocks that have ever been used.

Many sites will make an incremental level 0 backup every weekend. Then a level 1 backup can be made with this command:
backup as backupset incremental level 1 database;

This command could be run daily, to extract all blocks changed since the last level 1 (or, the first time it is run, the level 0) backup. 
A cumulative incremental backup might be run mid-week:
backup as backupset cumulative database;
This will extract all blocks changed since the level 0 backup.

RMAN uses a repository to store details of all the backup operations it has carried out. This repository is the key to automated restore and recovery, and the source of reports on backups. During a backup operation, RMAN will write to its repository all detail of the backup: what was backed up, where the backup files are, the time and system change number of certain events, and so on.

The repository is stored in the database’s controlfile. This does raise the question of what to do if the controlfile itself needs to be restored. There are techniques to cover this situation (dealt with in the second OCP examination) by creating a separate database known as the Recovery Manager Catalog, and by creating automatic backups of the controlfile to a well-known location. At this stage, the assumption is that the controlfile is protected by multiplexing, so there will always be at least one copy of it available.

Reports on Backups
RMAN has two commands that will tell you the state of your backup: LIST will tell you what backups there are, REPORT will tell you what backups are needed. Examples from the RMAN command line are
list backup of database;
list backup of archivelog all;
report need backup;
report obsolete;

The first of these commands will list all the backups that have been made and are still recorded in the repository.
The second command lists all backups of archived red log files.
The third command lists everything that needs to be backed up according to the Recovery Manager’s configured retention policy (such as three
backups of every file). 
The final command lists all backups that are no longer needed according to the Recovery Manager’s configured retention policy.

From the RMAN command line,there are four critical commands:
■ CROSSCHECK A crosscheck forces RMAN to compare its repository with the real world. It will check that all the backups it has made do still exist, on disk or tape. Any that it finds to be missing are flagged as EXPIRED.
■ DELETE EXPIRED This will remove all references from the repository to expired backups. If the backups have merely been moved (off site, perhaps), an alternative is to mark them as UNAVAILABLE.
■ DELETE OBSOLETE This will force RMAN to apply its retention policy. It will delete all backups that it considers to be no longer necessary from disk
or tape, and remove the references to them from its repository.
■ CATALOG This command lets you inform RMAN about additional user-managed backups, so that RMAN can include them in its repository. If backups have been moved, CATALOG can also be used to tell RMAN the new locations

Monitoring the Flash Recovery Area
Once use of a flash recovery area has been configured, it is vital to monitor how much space is being taken up within it.
From the database home page take the Availability tab, and then the Recovery Settings link in the Setup section. The flash recovery area is shown in the bottom part of the window.

The same information could be obtained by querying the views V$RECOVERY_FILE_DEST and V$FLASH_RECOVERY_AREA_USAGE

-------------------- Biju Thomas
Control File Architecture
The control file is a relatively small (in the megabyte range) binary file that contains information about the structure of the database. You can think of the control file as a metadata repository for the physical database.

The contents of the control file include the following:
The database name to which the control file belongs. A control file can belong to only one database.
The database-creation timestamp.
The name, location, and online/offline status information of the data files.
The name and location of the redo log files.
Redo log archive information.
Tablespace names.
The current log sequence number, which is a unique identifier that is incremented and recorded when an online redo log file is switched.
The most recent checkpoint information.
The beginning and ending of undo segments.
Recovery Manager’s backup information. Recovery Manager (RMAN) is the Oracle utility you use to back up and recover databases.

Understanding Checkpoints
The CKPT process controls the amount of time required for instance recovery. During a checkpoint, CKPT updates the control file and the header of the data files to reflect the last successful transaction by recording the last system change number (SCN). The SCN, which is a number sequentially assigned to each transaction in the database, is also recorded in the control file against the data file name that is taken offline or made read-only.

The LGWR process writes redo information from the redo log buffer to the online redo log files under a variety of circumstances:
When a user commits a transaction, even if this is the only transaction in the log buffer 
When the redo log buffer becomes one-third full
When the buffer contains approximately 1MB of changed records; this total does not include deleted or inserted records
When a database checkpoint is performed
LGWR always writes its records to the online redo log file before DBWn writes new or modified database buffer cache records to the data files.

Creating New Groups
You can create and add more redo log groups to the database by using the ALTER DATABASE command. The following statement creates a new log file group with two members:
ALTER DATABASE ADD LOGFILE
GROUP 3 (‘/ora02/oradata/MYDB01/redo0301.log’,
‘/ora03/oradata/MYDB01/redo0302.log’) SIZE 10M;

If you omit the GROUP clause, Oracle assigns the next available number. For example, the following statement also creates a multiplexed group:

ALTER DATABASE ADD LOGFILE
(‘/ora02/oradata/MYDB01/redo0301.log’,
‘/ora03/oradata/MYDB01/redo0302.log’) SIZE 10M;

To create a new group without multiplexing, use the following statement:

ALTER DATABASE ADD LOGFILE
‘/ora02/oradata/MYDB01/redo0301.log’ REUSE;

You can add more than one redo log group by using the ALTER DATABASE command—just use a comma to separate the groups.

