Performing Database Recovery

The terms restore and recover have precise meanings in the Oracle environment. To restore a file is to extract it from a backup and return it to the place where it was made. But the restored file will be out of date compared to the rest of the database. To recover the file, extract the relevant change vectors from the redo log stream and apply them to bring the file forward in time until it is synchronized with the rest of the database.

Depending on the type of file that is lost, there are different techniques for recovery

Recovery from Loss of the Controlfile
A point to emphasize is that the controlfile should never be completely lost: it should be multiplexed, so that if one copy of it is lost, another copy will still be available. If any copy of the controlfile is damaged, the database instance will abort immediately. If you attempt a startup, the instance will go nomount mode but will stop there: it will not mount the database unless all copies of the controlfile, as specified by the CONTROL_FILES instance parameter, are valid.

If the startup stops in nomount mode because the database cannot be mounted, determine what controlfile copies it is looking for with this query:

select value from v$parameter where name='control_files';

To confirm that the controlfile is multiplexed, when in mount mode or open mode issue this query:

select name from v$controlfile;

To find which copy is damaged or missing, look in the alert log. This is the file alert_instancename.ora in the directory specified by the BACKGROUND_DUMP_DEST parameter. The last few lines will be something like this:
ORA-00210: cannot open the specified control file
ORA-00202: control file: 'D:\APP\ORACLE\ORADATA\ORCL11G\CONTROL02.CTL'
ORA-27041: unable to open file
OSD-04002: unable to open file

To repair the damage, copy a surviving file (one of the files listed in the query against V$PARAMETER) over the damaged file (the file mentioned in the alert log).

Recovery from Loss of an Online Redo Log File Member
If your online redo log file groups are multiplexed, loss of a single member is not a problem. As long as there is at least one valid member of each online redo log file group, the database will continue running, and if it is shut down, it will open without a problem. But Oracle will not be happy: there will be many messages written out to the alert log.
To confirm whether the online redo log file members are multiplexed and to see the status of each file, run this query:
select * from v$logfile;

If any members have a STATUS of INVALID, you should take immediate action to correct the situation. The status STALE may be reported—this is not a problem; it only shows that the file has not yet been used.

To repair a damaged member, the simplest technique is to use the CLEAR command. This will instruct Oracle to delete and recreate all the members of log file group 3: 
alter database clear logfile group 3;
If the log file group is current, active, or (in archivelog mode) unarchived, the CLEAR will fail with an appropriate error message. These commands will fix these issues:

alter system switch logfile;
alter system checkpoint;
alter system archive log all;

Loss of Any Datafile in Noarchivelog Mode
In noarchivelog mode, there can be no concept of recovery: the redo needed to bring a restored backup forward in time isn’t available. It is not possible to open a database with a datafile that is out of date. If it were, the integrity of the system would be compromised.

So if any file is damaged, the only options are to instruct Oracle never to look for the file again by dropping the tablespace of which it is a part, or to restore the entire database: the complete set of datafiles and the controlfile from the last backup. If you have the online redo log files as well (which you will usually have if you are doing user-managed backups), restore these too and open the database. If you do not have backups of the online redo log files, recreate them by opening the database with this command:

alter database open resetlogs;

Loss of a Datafile in Archivelog Mode

The datafiles that make up the SYSTEM and UNDO tablespaces are critical. If any of these is damaged while the database is open, it will abort. The other datafiles are non-critical: the database will take them offline automatically, and the database will remain open.

if the damaged or missing datafile is critical it will not be possible to open the database until it has been restored and recovered. If the datafile is non-critical, it must be taken offline manually before the database can be opened, and then it can be restored and recovered while the database is open.

If the database is shut down, the steps to repair a damaged non-critical datafile are
■ Mount the database.
■ Take the damaged file(s) offline.
■ Open the database.
■ Restore the damaged file(s).
■ Recover it (them).
■ Bring the damaged file(s) online.
If the database is open, only the last three steps are necessary.

Damage to a critical datafile can only be repaired in mount mode, so there are four steps:
■ Mount the database.
■ Restore the damaged file(s).
■ Recover it (them).
■ Open the database.

The Health Monitor and the ADR

The Health Monitor is a set of checks that run automatically when certain error conditions arise, or manually in response to the DBA’s instructions. The results of the checks are not stored in the database, but in the file system. This is because the nature of some errors is such that the database is not available: it is therefore essential to have an external repository for the Health Monitor results. This repository is the ADR, which is located in the directory specified by the DIAGNOSTIC_DEST instance parameter.

The interfaces that will allow manual running of Health Monitor checks are available only when the database is open. There are two interfaces: using SQL*Plus to invoke procedures in the DBMS_HM PL/SQL package, and Database Control.

Database Control -> advisor central-> checkers

Use Data Recovery Advisor to Perform Recovery

The DRA makes use of information gathered by the Health Monitor to find problems, and then it constructs RMAN scripts to repair them. As with any RMAN-based utility, the instance must be started.

The flow for using the DRA is as follows:
■ Assess data failures The Health Monitor, running reactively or on demand, will write error details to the ADR.
■ List failures The DRA will list all failures, classified according to severity.
■ Advise on repair The DRA will generate RMAN scripts to repair the damage.
■ Execute repair Run the scripts.


If one or more failures exist, then you should typically use LIST FAILURE to show information about the failures and then use ADVISE FAILURE in the
same RMAN session to obtain a report of your repair options. Finally, REPAIR FAILURE will fix the problem.

ADVISE FAILURE prepares a rman script which can be viewed. and REPAIR FAILURE runs this script to fix the problem.

The DRA works, but you can often do better. For example, it does not generate scripts that will minimize downtime by opening the database before doing the restore and recovery (which would be possible in the example).

The Capabilities and Limitations of the DRA

The DRA can do nothing unless the instance is in nomount mode, or higher. It follows that it cannot assist if there is a problem with the initialization file. In nomount mode, it can diagnose problems with the controlfile and generate scripts to restore it, either by using an existing valid copy or (if none is available) by extracting a copy from a backup set—provided it can find one. Once the database can reach mount mode, the DRA can diagnose problems with missing or damaged datafiles and missing online log file groups, and generate repair scripts.

The DRA (in the current release) only supports single-instance databases. If a fault brings down a RAC database, you can mount it in single-instance mode, use the DRA to repair the damage, and then shut it down and reopen it in RAC mode.