Backup and Recovery Concepts

So to summarize, because LGWR always writes ahead of DBWn, and because it writes in real time on commit, there will always be enough information in the redo stream to reconstruct any committed changes that had not been written to the datafiles, and to roll back any uncommitted changes that had been written to the data files.

The parameter FAST_START_MTTR_TARGET defaults to zero. This has the effect of maximizing performance, with the possible cost of long instance recovery times after an instance failure. The DBWn process will write as little as it can get away with, meaning that the checkpoint position may be a long way out of date and that therefore a large amount of redo would have to be applied to the datafiles in the roll forward phase of instance recovery.

Setting FAST_START_MTTR_TARGET to a non-zero value has two effects.
First, it sets a target for recovery,
also a secondary effect: enabling checkpoint auto-tuning. The checkpoint auto-tuning mechanism inspects statistics on machine utilization, such as the rate of disk I/O and CPU usage, and if it appears that there is spare capacity, it will use this capacity to write out additional dirty buffers from the database buffer cache, thus pushing the checkpoint position forward.

------------- Biju Thomas book ---------------
However, if FAST_START_MTTR_TARGET is set to a low nonzero value, writes to the redo logs most likely have to wait for writes to the data files. Although this reduces the amount of time it takes to recover the instance in the case of an instance failure, it affects performance and response time. Setting this value too high can result in an unacceptable amount of time needed to recover the instance after an instance failure.

------------------------------------------

Enabling checkpoint auto-tuning with a high target should result in your instance always having the fastest possible recovery time that is consistent with maximum performance.

More complete information can be gained from querying the V$INSTANCE_RECOVERY view

Column : Meaning
recovery_estimated_ios : The number of read/write operations that would be needed on datafiles for recovery if the instance crashed now
actual_redo_blocks : The number of OS blocks of redo that would need to be applied to datafiles for recovery if the instance crashed now
estimated_mttr : The number of seconds it would take to open the database if it crashed now
target_mttr : The setting of fast_start_mttr_target
writes_mttr : The number of times DBWn had to write, in addition to the writes it would normally have done, to meet the target mttr

Checkpointing is the process of forcing the DBWn to write dirty buffers from the database buffer cache to the datafiles.
The checkpoint position is advanced automatically by the DBWn. This process is known as incremental checkpointing. In addition, there may be full checkpoints and partial checkpoints.
A full checkpoint occurs when all dirty buffers are written to disk. This will entail a great deal of work: very high CPU and disk usage while the checkpoint is in progress, and reduced performance for user sessions. Full checkpoints are bad for business. Because of this, there will never be a full checkpoint except in two circumstances: an orderly shutdown, or at the DBA’s request.

A partial checkpoint is necessary and occurs automatically as part of certain operations. Depending on the operation, the partial checkpoint will affect different buffers. These are

Taking a tablespace offline : All blocks that are part of the tablespace will Be Flushed from the Cache
Taking a datafile offline : All blocks that are part of the datafile will Be Flushed from the Cache
Dropping a segment : All blocks that are part of the segment will Be Flushed from the Cache
Truncating a table : All blocks that are part of the table will Be Flushed from the Cache
Putting a tablespace into backup mode : All blocks that are part of the tablespace will Be Flushed from the Cache
 There
are two views that will tell you the state of your redo logs. V$LOG will have one row per group, and V$LOGFILE will have one row per log file member

alter system switch logfile;

after log switch if you query v$log , one group with status as current and another group as status acive will be found. The previously current group has status ACTIVE. This means that it would still be needed by SMON for instance recovery if the instance failed now. In a short time, as the checkpoint position advances, it will become INACTIVE. 
alter system checkpoint;
command would force the checkpoint position to come up-to-date, active would then become inactive immediately.

An online redo log file can be overwritten only if it is inactive, and (if the database is in archivelog mode) if it has been archived.

Archiver processes launch automatically if the database is in archivelog mode.

The Oracle instance takes care of creating the archive logs with the ARCn process, but the migration to tape must be controlled by the DBA, either through operating system commands or by using the recovery manager utility RMAN

Determine the archivelog mode of the database, and whether ARCn is running, with these commands:
select log_mode from v$database;
select archiver from v$instance;

The flash recovery area is a disk destination used as the default location for recovery related files. It is controlled with two instance parameters:
■ db_recovery_file_dest
■ db_recovery_file_dest_size

The first of these parameters nominates the location. This can be a file system directory, or an ASM disk group. It is possible for several databases to share a common destination; each database will have its own directory structure (created automatically) in the destination. The second parameter limits the amount of space in the destination that the database will occupy; it says nothing about how much space is actually available in the destination.

The files that will be written to the flash recovery area (unless specified otherwise) include
■ Recovery Manager backups
■ Archive redo log files
■ Database flashback logs

In an ideal situation, the flash recovery area will be large enough to store a complete copy of the database, plus any archive logs and incremental backups that would be necessary to recover the copy if necessary.

The database backup routines should also include backing up the flash recovery area to tape, thus implementing a strategy of primary, secondary, and tertiary storage:
■ Primary storage is the live database, on disk.
■ Secondary storage is a copy of the database plus files needed for fast recovery.
■ Tertiary storage is long-term backups in a tape library.

RMAN can manage the whole cycle: backup of the database from primary to secondary and migration of backups from secondary to tertiary storage.

The transition to archivelog mode is straightforward, but it does require downtime. The process is

■ Shut down the database, cleanly.
■ Start up in mount mode.
■ Issue the command ALTER DATABASE ARCHIVELOG.
■ Open the database.
■ Perform a full backup.